大帝在来的路上
The Emperor is coming.
那我们得跟他的继位者
We must avoid dishonor
搞好关系免遭羞辱
by cultivating goodwill with his successor.
你是指卡里古拉?
You mean Caligula?
你要是知道我们为何来此
You may not be so keen to welcome us
可能就不会这么热烈欢迎我们了
when you find out why we're here.
告诉我彼得在哪 我们就停手
Tell me where Peter is, and we'll stop.
我不觉得到撒玛利亚会有何益处 腓力
I don't think it will be any better in Samaria for them.
我帮你
Let me help you.
来这途中 我看见四只秃鹰
On the journey here, I saw four vultures.
这地方让你见到幻象
This place gives you visions.
西门魔法师!
Simon the sorcerer!
他觉得自己比我厉害
He thinks he can do what I can't.
奉耶稣之名 我将你从监牢中释放
In the name of Jesus, I release you from your prison.
你是否悔改你的罪?
Do you repent your sins?
我悔改
I do.
把彼得的消息告诉扫罗
Tell Saul about Peter.
- 他往北去了  - 哪里?
- He headed north.  - Where?
大马士革
Damascus.
本片涉及圣经内容的名词 段落 均参照和合本翻译
公元: 圣经续 第一季第8集
--==圣城家园SCG字幕组 http://hdscg.com/==--
一旦扫罗去往大马士革
We'll all sleep better
仅供翻译交流使用, 禁止用于商业用途
我们都能高枕无忧了
once Saul leaves for Damascus.
协调: 影子
果真如此?
Really?
你要确保他不会
Your task is to make sure he doesn't bring
翻译: 飘飘行天下 小黄不小黄 猫呗
翻译: 舒舒 鸟生鱼汤 波特妹子
再让耶路撒冷陷入暴乱...
his campaign of violence back to Jerusalem...
校对: 飘飘行天下 影子
尤其不能在提庇留回罗马之前
not before Tiberius has left for Rome.
那我要如何确保?
And how exactly do I do that?
你同他一起去
You're going with him.
我可不认为年轻活泼就该是这副模样
I won't defend this as youthful high spirits.
恕我冒昧... 我也很不想这样说...
Forgive me... and it pains me to say this...
这可不是未来君主应有的行为
This is not the behavior of a future emperor.
没错
I agree.
要能承担起将来的责任
Caligula has a great deal to learn
卡里古拉要学的东西还很多
about the responsibilities he will carry.
但他同这个犹太人阿格里帕整日厮混
But it doesn't help that he spends so much time
可毫无益处
with this Jew, Agrippa.
近墨者黑
He's a malign influence.
叫醒他们 让他们出去
Wake them. Get them out of here.
可不能让克劳迪娅看见
Claudia mustn't see this.
不能让克劳迪娅看见什么?
Claudia mustn't see what?
他们怎敢把我的名字写在烂醉的妓女身上
How dare they scrawl my name on a wine-soaked whore.
要是这淫行在屋里留下一丝痕迹
I will not set foot inside this room again
我便再不踏足半步
until every sign of this debauchery is gone.
要是能在日落前赶到拉马塔教区
If we reach Ramatha before sunset,
应该就能在两日内到达大马士革
we should make Damascus in two days.
扫罗 那里远在70英里外
Saul, that's over 70 Miles away,
你难道想一日内赶到?
and you want to do that in a day,
这一路都是荒漠和山路
over open deserts and Mountain tracks
还是三伏天呢
in the hottest month?
看起来我们新来的人
It would appear our new recruit
更想窝在家里呢
would be happier staying at home.
我可不要走这么快 会要了命的
I'm not going to kill myself marching at that pace.
听说腓力需要我们
We get word that Philip needs us.
必须有人去撒玛利亚
Somebody has to go to Samaria.
那我们怎么办?
So what do we do?
就躲在一个地窖里
We hide in a cellar.
西门 我明白你的心情
Simon, I feel the same way.
但只要扫罗一日在那...
But as long as Saul's out there...
我知道跟腓力会合很危险
I know going to join Philip is dangerous,
但我不想当个懦夫
but I feel like a coward.
那么现在你不必当懦夫了
Well, now you don't need to.
扫罗走了
Saul's gone.
他离开了耶路撒冷
He's left Jerusalem.
约翰 我们今夜就赶去撒玛利亚
We'll go to Samaria tonight, John.
玛利亚? 是我... 约亚拿
Mary? It's me... Joanna.
你在这里做什么?
What are you doing here?
我是随安提帕的家宰来的
I'm here with the house of Antipas,
来服侍希罗底
maid-servant to Herodias.
你是在宫殿里作工吗?
Are you working in the palace?
我们得小心 这里的人与我们信仰不同
We must be cautious. None here share our faith.
彼得也在这里吗?
Is Peter here, too?
他在城里... 安全躲着呢
He's in the city... hiding, safe.
自从耶稣治好我俩的病 我就整日想着你
I thought about you every day since Jesus cured us.
我也想遵行他讲的道 但是...
I have tried to follow his word, but...
我听说他已经死了
I heard he was dead.
约亚拿...
Joanna...
耶稣并没死
Jesus isn't dead.
在他上十字架前
Before they crucified him,
他就告诉我们他将在三日后复活
he told us he would rise after three days,
后来果真如此
and he did.
他活得好好的
He's very much alive.
是真的
No. It's true.
他先来找我
He came to me first.
我与他同坐 与他同吃
I've sat with him, eaten with him.
他真如他所说
He is who he said he was.
是弥赛亚
He is the Messiah.
我一度还挺喜欢阿格里帕 但是如今...
I was fond of Agrippa once, but now...
我该处死他吗?
Should I have him killed?
不用
No.
您带卡里古拉回罗马
Take Caligula back to Rome with you,
由我丈夫来处置阿格里帕
and my husband will deal with Agrippa.
彼拉多是个好巡抚
Pilate is a good governor.
您只要看看
You only have to see
耶路撒冷清静无事的街道就知道他...
the trouble-free streets of Jerusalem to see what...
为了让你丈夫升官你真是煞费苦心
You work hard to promote your husband.
等我把他升迁到罗马去的时候
I'm sure he will benefit from your wisdom
你的智慧一定对他大有裨益
when I promote him to a position in Rome.
谢谢您
Thank you.
我不知道我更高兴的是哪件事...
I don't know what pleases me more...
是可以去罗马多陪陪您
the thought of spending more time in your company in Rome
还是终于可以...
or finally being able to...
有什么问题吗?
Is there something wrong?
没有
No.
感觉有点凉 没什么
Just a chill. That's all.
不要低估了彼得
Do not underestimate Peter.
他是个卖狗皮膏药的 但是非常在行
He is a snake-oil trader, but a good one.
他先告诉大家他们有麻烦了...
First, he tells the people that they have a problem...
说他们杀了神派给他们的人
that they killed the man sent to them by God.
然后他再说他有解决方法
Then he tells them that he has the answer.
他们只需要
All they have to do
忏悔 然后跳到河里去就可以了
is repent and throw themselves in the river.
他就不能消停会吗?
Does he ever stop?
我从来没见过为了毁灭敌人
I never saw a man with so much energy
如此干劲十足的人
for the destruction of his enemies.
我们现在... 坐在这里... 作为被选中的少数人
And here we sit... now... the chosen few,
我们的使命是根除这个异教
whose work it is to stamp out this heresy
不能让它从耶路撒冷
before it spreads from Jerusalem
散布到叙利亚 吕大 以马忤斯 甚至是马察达去
and takes control of Syria, Lydda, Emmaus, and even Masada,
不能让彼得这个渔夫把他那虚假的解药
before Peter the fisherman can sell the whole world
卖给全世界
his fake cure.
这里大多数人都认为罗马人很堕落
Most people here believe all Romans to be degenerate.
你想证明他们是对的吗?
Are you determined to prove them right?
你听到什么了吗?
Do you hear something?
噪音...
A noise...
就像母牛在叫
like a cow breaking wind.
最糟的是 你侮辱了我的妻子
On top of that, you insult my wife.
如果一个人的妻子是婊子的女儿
Is it possible to insult a man's wife
还怎么侮辱她呢?
when she's the daughter of a whore?
收回那些话 不然我就割了你的喉咙
Take back those words before I open your throat.
来啊
Do it.
我想着提庇留会怎么对付你
I'd almost die happy
会死得很开心的
thinking about what Tiberius would do to you.
起来啊 你这头蠢马!
Get up, you stupid animal!
走啊
Come on.
我本该下手的
I should've done it.
他说了这种话我就该割了他的喉咙
I should've slit his throat after what he said.
要是你杀了他 你还能活多久?
And how long would you have lived if you had?
然后把阿格里帕也杀了
And done the same with Agrippa.
你也可以忽视他们
Or your could ignore them both
期待一下罗马的生活
and look forward to life in Rome.
我还从来没见过如此居心叵测 卑鄙狠毒
I've never come across such treacherous, poisonous,
渴望权力的阴谋家
power-hungry schemers.
怎么了?
What is it?
我希望那里的一切
I'm looking forward to everything there
都能少点...
being a lot less...
犹太风格
Jewish.
你呢?
Aren't you?
你在说什么 克劳迪娅?
What are you talking about, Claudia?
提庇留要升你去罗马了
Tiberius has offered you a position in Rome.
终于
At last.
我们终于可以离开这地方了
We can finally leave this place.
我们只需要
All we have to do
做好我们的事
is play our part
让阿格里帕和卡里古拉分开
in keeping Agrippa and Caligula away from each other.
我奉圣父 圣子
I baptize you in the name of the father
和圣灵的名为你施洗
and of the son and of the Holy Spirit.
彼得! 约翰!
Peter! John!
见到你们真高兴
It's so good to see you both.
朋友们 如今我们将自己交托给耶稣
My friends, today, we commit ourselves to Jesus,
而这两个人认识他
who these two men knew
并从他那里得到了圣灵的能力
and from him received the power of the Holy Spirit.
如果连弥赛亚的名字也不敢说
How can we celebrate the Messiah
还如何颂扬他?
when we dare not say his name?
我害怕
I'm scared.
不必害怕
Don't be.
我们共同祈祷 你的信仰便可给你力量
Your faith will bring you strength when we pray together.
苦撒
Chuza.
我没想到你会现在回来
I wasn't expecting you back.
这是我的丈夫
This is my husband.
那这位是谁?
And who is this?
玛利亚
Mary.
我才刚刚开始在这个宫殿工作
I only just started work here in the palace,
但我认识约亚拿...
but I know Joanna from...
集市上认识的
From the market.
我们以前常在集市上碰到
We used to see each other at the market.
我们不是说好了
Didn't we agree
只要交了新朋友都要告诉我吗?
you need to tell me about any new friends?
我夫人最近受了一些不好的影响
My wife has come under some bad influences recently.
我不想再发生这种事
I don't want it to happen again.
不要担心 我会保护她的
Don't worry. I'll keep her from harm.
你的丈夫不知道你的信仰吗?
Your husband doesn't know about your faith?
他知道的
He does.
安全起见 我同意保密
I agreed to hide it to protect us both.
安提帕和希罗底
It was Antipas and Herodias
把施洗者约翰的头砍了
that had John the baptist beheaded.
我们伺候的就是这样无情的人
These are ruthless people we work for.
你觉得他会把你供出来吗?
Do you think he'd give you away?
不 他不会那么做的
No. He wouldn't do that.
哦
Ooh.
我们又弄脏了一个女仆
We've soiled another serving girl.
哦
Oh.
干嘛这么严肃?
Why so serious?
只是开个玩笑
It's just a bit of fun.
我们离这死气沉沉的地方远一点
Let's get out of this mausoleum
去找些合适的女人
and find some proper women.
你也太挑剔了
You're far too choosy.
成熟的果实就在眼前 我的朋友却视而不见
My friend doesn't know ripe fruit when he sees it.
请原谅 我们得...
Forgive us. We need...
你可以下去了
You can leave us.
你是聋了还是太蠢?
Are you deaf or just stupid?
走开
Leave us.
我还要为你姐姐希罗底做事
I... I have work to do for your sister, Herodias.
她不会介意你和我共度片刻
She won't mind if you spend a few minutes with me.
我亲爱的弟弟
My dear brother.
我早同你讲过...
I've told you before...
别让我逮到你玩弄我的东西
don't let me catch you playing with my things.
扫罗
Saul.
扫罗!
Saul!
扫罗 这地方太疯狂了
Saul, this place is madness.
要是你没找到他呢?
What if you don't find him?
要是彼得根本不在大马士革呢?
What if Peter's not even in Damascus?
我们要追到安提阿吗?
Do we march onto Antioch?
你究竟来这里干嘛? 嗯?
Why are you even here? Huh?
我来这里是因为受命来此
I'm here because I was ordered to be here
我们听命于同一人
by the same man we both answer to.
那你就该协助完成这一使命
Then you should be helping this mission,
而非拖拉时间
not slowing it down.
你为什么这么恨彼得?
Why do you hate Peter so much?
因为他的话太荒谬
Because his claims are ridiculous.
因为说他是神拣选的
Because the idea that God would use him
神的旨意的器皿
as an instrument of his will
让他传扬新的弥赛亚的道
to spread the word of a new Messiah
这想法... 太荒谬了
is... is ridiculous.
人们怎能相信造物主会选择
How can people believe that the creator would choose
一个卑微的渔夫来表达他的旨意?
a simple fisherman to articulate his message?
不 不
No. No.
他会选择一个
He would choose a man
比渔村之徒眼界开阔的人
who knew a world outside of a fishing village,
而不是替骗子耶稣散播谎言的人
not a man who spreads lies about an impostor Jesus,
会选一个为他的旨意
but a man who can add beauty and power and truth
增光添彩的人... 比如...
to his message... a man like...
好吧
Yeah.
扫罗
Saul.
你为什么逼迫我?
Why do you persecute me?
你是谁?
Who are you?
我就是
I am Jesus.
你所逼迫的耶稣
Whom you persecute.
不
No.
不 不! 不!
No. No! No!
你要我... 你要我怎样?
What do you... What do you want from me?
你要我怎样?
What do you want from me?
你要我怎样?!
What do you want from me?!
去大马士革
Go into Damascus.
你所当作的事 必有人告诉你
You'll be told what to do.
帮帮我
Help me.
来人啊!
Someone!
帮帮我!
Help me!
救我!!
Help me!!
大马士革
扫罗...
Saul...
你得吃点东西
You have to eat something.
我知道你们有些人想回到家人身边
I know some of you want to be back with your families,
我也知道大马士革满是外邦人
and I know Damascus is full of foreigners
食物也太贵
and the food is overpriced.
但我们和扫罗一同来此 目的明确
But we came here with Saul, and we know why we're here.
带我们来此的是个了不起的人
The man who brought us is a remarkable man.
不管在沙漠中发生什么事 我们都不能放弃
Whatever happened to him in the desert, we can't give up.
我们必须找到彼得和追随他的人
We must find Peter and his followers.
撒玛利亚
我自欺欺人
I was deluded.
用雕虫小技骗倒众人后
I was deceiving people with my cheap trickery,
我开始相信我真有自己宣称的能力
and I started to believe my own claims of greatness.
然后腓利 他来到了撒玛利亚
And then Philip, he came to Samaria.
他向我指明道路
He showed me the true path.
他说起了耶稣 我就相信了他
He started talking about Jesus, and I believed.
我受了洗礼
I was baptized.
在耶路撒冷我们不受神殿所爱
We are not loved by the temple in Jerusalem,
你也一样
and neither are you.
好吧... 我们应该一起传扬耶稣的道
Well... well, together, we shall help to spread the word
传扬他的能力 好吗?
and the power of Jesus, eh?
他们已经听说了你在耶路撒冷
They, uh, they've heard all about the miracles
施行的奇迹
you performed in Jerusalem.
他们希望在撒玛利亚能有更多奇迹
They hope to see more here in Samaria.
我的孩子快生下来了 巴拿巴
My child is coming, Barnabas.
我得离开大马士革
I have to leave Damascus.
什么?
What?
我刚才看到了流便
I just saw Reuben,
大祭司该亚法的得力手下
the right-hand man to high priest Caiaphas,
还有亚设 扫罗的手下
and Asher, one of Saul's men.
扫罗在大马士革
Saul is in Damascus.
你来到这里给我们灌输
You arrive here and you fill our heads
救主耶稣基督的力量
with the power of Jesus Christ the savior,
却一见危险就要退缩
and now you cower at the first sign of danger.
亚拿尼亚!
Ananias!
大数人扫罗 他想杀了我...
Saul of Tarsus, who wants me dead...
想杀了我们所有人... 他在这里
who wants us all dead... is here.
那我该怎么做?
And what am I supposed to do?
告诉我妻子 先不要生孩子了
Tell my wife, don't have our child yet.
赶紧离开这里?
We have to leave the city?
留下吧
Stay.
留下来
我们共同寻求力量
And we'll find strength together.
倚靠耶稣
Trust in Jesus.
让圣灵进入你困苦的肢体
Let the Holy Spirit into your troubled limbs.
他赐给你永生
He brings you eternal life.
你当信服耶稣基督
Have faith in Jesus Christ.
他便是那路 是真理 是生命
He is the way, the truth, and the life.
我们祈祷新的信徒
We pray that all our new believers
都蒙受圣灵
receive the Holy Spirit.
难以置信
Unbelievable.
我们向神悔改 信靠我主 蒙他悦纳
We enter God's kingdom by repentance and faith
进入神的国
by accepting him in our lives.
等你回到罗马...
When you return to Rome...
根据这份文件 你会被考虑
this document says you'll be considered
任职掌管国库
for the position of praetor to the treasury.
被考虑?
Considered?
我的印章保证你会出任
And my seal on it says you will get the job.
凯撒 我不知该如何表达谢意
Caesar, I don't know how to show you my gratitude.
那就勤勉工作吧
By doing the job well.
还有 永远听从你妻子的建议
And by always listening to your wife's advice.
这下好了 这是正式命令
There. It's official.
永远听从你的妻子
Always listen to your wife.
我会记住的!
I won't forget this!
你在说什么?
What are you talking about?
你就这么懦弱只敢在背后阴我们?
Are you such a coward you have to go behind our backs?
又喝酒了 是吗?
Been drinking again, have we?
提庇留坚持让我和他一起去罗马
Tiberius is insisting I go with him to Rome
让阿格里帕留在这里
and Agrippa stays here.
我知道这是你们密谋的结果
I know it is a result of your plotting.
相信我... 当我看不到你的时候
Believe me... when I'm not in your presence,
我从来没有想到过你
I don't give you a moment's thought.
他以为他能拆散我们
He thinks he can break the bond between us.
但是他错了
But he is wrong.
如果你觉得提庇留总是能护着你
Now, you make a very grave mistake
那你就犯了一个非常严重的错误
if you think Tiberius will always protect you.
彼拉多 你会为你的阴谋付出代价的!
Pilate, you will pay for your scheming!
你将俯首听命!
And you will answer to me!
You will answer to me!
彼得
Peter.
这... 这是我所有身家
This... this is everything that I own.
我希望你可以用它
I want you to use it
帮助传扬耶稣的道
to help spread the word of Jesus.
我想要的回报仅仅是...
Now, all I want in return is just...
你知道的 仅仅是一些圣灵的能力...
you know, just a few drops of the Holy Spirit...
作为朋友
as a friend.
作为同伴 耶稣的追随者
as a fellow Jesus follower.
怎么样?
Yeah?
你以为神是可以用钱买的?
You think God can be bought?
你觉得这只是魔法?!
You think this is just magic?!
彼得! 住手!
Peter! Stop!
不要发怒!
Hold your anger!
嘿! 收回你说的话!
Hey! Take back your words!
忏悔!
Repent!
要是你还看重性命就快点忏悔!
If you value your life, repent now!
我忏悔!
I repent!
求求你 主!
Please, Lord!
求你怜恤此人!
Show mercy to this man!
我恳求你!
I beg you!
饶他一命!
Let him live!
彼得
Peter.
倘若这不是你的道
If it isn't your word,
不是你为你的仆人所谋之事
isn't a part of your plan for your servants.
但正如你照看我们
But as you watch over us,
我祈求你帮助我丈夫体谅之
I pray that you help my husband understand.
他是一个好人
He's a good man.
我奉你儿子耶稣的名祈祷...
I pray in the name of your son, Jesus...
他为救我们而死
who died that we might be saved.
若你喜悦 让苏撒拿发现耶稣的智慧
If it pleases you, let Chuza discover the wisdom of Jesus.
如若不喜 我恳求...
If it does not, I ask very...
克劳迪娅
Claudia.
不管梦到什么 不过是梦而已
Whatever it was, it was just a dream.
怎么了?
What is it?
什么东西这么可怕?
What was so terrible?
没什么
It's nothing.
亚拿尼亚
Ananias.
主
Lord.
往直街去
Go to the street called straight.
找一个大数人
Ask for a man from Tarsus.
名叫扫罗
His name is Saul.
但我知道这人怎样在耶路撒冷多多苦害
But I know the harm that this man has done
你的圣徒
to your people in Jerusalem.
他是我所拣选的器皿
He is my chosen instrument.
要在外邦人和君王并以色列人面前
He will proclaim my name to the gentiles and their kings
宣扬我的名
and the people of Israel.
什么?
What?
住手 伙计! 你不能!
Stop, mate! You mustn't!
亚拿尼亚
Ananias.
得有人回耶路撒冷
Someone needs to go to Jerusalem
把这发生的事告诉该亚法
and tell Caiaphas what's happening.
该告诉他什么呢?
And tell him what, exactly?
让他知道他的红人 阻止亵渎神灵之人
That his golden boy, his great weapon
东山再起的得力干将
against the rise of these blasphemers
正在黑暗中
is sitting in the dark
把自己饿死?
starving himself to death?
或许我能帮忙
Perhaps I can help.
我有消息要给大数人扫罗...
I have a message for Saul of Tarsus...
很重要的消息
an important one.
来自何人?
From whom?
来自... 某个对他很了解的人...
From... someone who knows him well...
可以说 比任何人都了解他
knows him better than anyone, I'd say.
那么你是...?
And you are...?
我是亚拿尼亚
I am Ananias.
他来了吗?
I.. is he here?
亚拿尼亚在哪儿? 在这里吗?
Where's Ananias? Is he here?
- 我在这  - 哦 哦
- I'm here.  - Oh. Oh.
求你... 救救我
Save me from this... please.
他拣选了你 叫你明白他的旨意
He has chosen you to know his will
又得见那义者
and to see the righteous one
听他口中所出的声音
and to hear the words from his mouth.
他能看见了
He can see.
扫罗又能看见了
Saul can see again.
我能看见了!
I can see!
谢谢你 谢谢你 谢谢你
Thank you. Thank you. Thank you.
把我和卡里古拉分开又把我困在此处
Separate me from Caligula and keep me in this place,
至少也该尊重我
but at least show me some respect.
照我所说惩罚这些亵渎神灵的人
Do as I ask and punish these blasphemers.
这是你的职责 你要做出表率
It's your duty. Make an example of them.
职责? 什么时候你开始知道职责了?
Duty? Since when have you had any thoughts of duty?
他是对的... 尽管我质疑他的动机
He's right... though I do question his reasons.
他对这个女人有兴趣
He has an interest in this woman.
苦撒 我的家宰
Chuza, as my chief Steward,
你知道背叛的后果
you know the consequences of betrayal.
果真如此吗?
Is it true?
你的妻子是那个人称耶稣的拿撒勒人的信徒吗?
Is your wife a follower of the Nazarene they call Jesus?
我听见你向他祷告
I heard you pray to him.
只要...
Just...
实话实说就好
give us the truth.
事实是... 那个 呃...
The truth is... that, uh...
事实是...
The truth is...
我的妻子约亚拿自从结婚以来
that my wife, Joanna, ever since we were married,
都会不时发疯
has had fits of madness.
自从有了关于那个拿撒勒人
Since all the talk began of the Nazarene
死而复生的传言 她就...
coming back to life after being crucified, she's...
嗯 她就整日想着此事
well, she's been taken by the idea.
有时她会臆想自己在跟他说话
And sometimes she imagines she's talking to him.
我怕有一天 她会陷入疯狂...
My fear is that one day, she'll slip into lunacy...
无法恢复
and not return.
你是说你的妻子并不是耶稣的信徒...
Your argument is that your wife isn't a follower of Jesus...
她只是疯了?
she's just mad?
女人 你又怎么说?
And what do you say, woman?
你是... 疯了?
What are you... mad?
没错
It's true.
我已不再鬼迷心窍
I was once cured of demons.
我不允许我家有人向那个人祷告...
I do not allow prayers to that man in my household...
哪怕是臆想也不行
even imagined ones.
管好你的妻子
Control your wife.
够了 让他们走吧
Enough. Let them go.
什么?!
What?!
就这样?!
That's all?!
你能恢复真是太好了
It's good to have you back.
好吧 我敞开心扉
Well, I open my heart,
感谢神宽恕了我
and I give my thanks to God for his forgiveness.
在沙漠的时候... 发生了什么?
What happened to you... in the desert?
我看见他
I saw him.
亲眼所见
I saw.
我看见耶稣基督 神的儿子
I saw Jesus Christ, the son of God.
他就在这
And he's here.
那些被我迫害的信徒
His presence is here on earth,
就是他存在的见证
through those followers I persecuted.
我曾经那么确定我是对的
I felt so sure that I was right,
但我...
but I...
我才是错了的人
I was the one that was wrong.
我们所有人都...
All of us just...
错了
wrong.
我必须将功赎罪 必须这样
I have to make amends. I have to.
所以我去了河边
So I'm going to the river
接受了这个人的洗礼... 亚拿尼亚
to be baptized by this man... Ananias.
而我恳求你们... 跟我一起
And I implore you... come with me.
感受神的爱
Feel God's love.
奉耶稣的名受洗
Be baptized in the name of Jesus.
太荒唐了
This is ridiculous.
你愚蠢的梦让我无法入睡
You're keeping me awake with your foolish dream.
告诉我
Tell me now.
你看到了什么?
What is it you're seeing?
我看见... 提庇留
I see... Tiberius.
看见他被杀死在床上
I see him murdered in his bed.
我还看到当他们用枕头捂住他的脸时
And I see him struggle
他... 他不断挣扎
as... as they hold a pillow over his face.
拿枕头的人是卡里古拉
The pillow is held by Caligula.
胡说
Nonsense.
是你想象力太丰富
It's your fanciful imaginings.
帮帮我
Help me.
来人啊!
Someone!
帮帮我!
Help me!!
我看见耶稣基督 神的儿子
I saw Jesus Christ, the son of God.
你怎敢奢求救赎 扫罗
How can you hope for salvation, Saul,
明知你的双手沾满了耶稣信徒的
when you have the blood of those who chose Jesus
鲜血?
on your hands?
你说得对
You're right.
我希望...
And I hope...
那些被我迫害过的人...
that all the people I persecuted...
他们可以发自内心地原谅我
they can find it in their hearts to forgive me.
我已经不是那个你们理应憎恨的人了
I'm not the same man you once had reason to hate.
我以前眼盲
I was blind.
而如今目明了
Now I see.
巴拿巴
Barnabas.
扫罗想受洗接受耶稣
Saul wants to be baptized to accept Jesus.
我们怎能拒绝他呢?
How can we deny him that?
耶稣拣选了你
Jesus has chosen you
要在外邦人和君王并以色列人面前...
to proclaim his name to the world...to the gentiles, their kings,
宣扬他的名
and the sons of Israel.
我奉圣父 圣子和圣灵的名
I baptize you in the name of the father and of the son
为你洗礼
and of the Holy Spirit.
我受洗了
I'm baptized.
现在我可以传扬耶稣基督的道了!
Now I can spread the word of Jesus Christ!
如果他原谅我 我会在耶稣里面得了丰盛!
If he will forgive me, I will be complete in Jesus!
巴拿巴!
Barnabas!
流便! 你怎么了?
Reuben! What's happened to you?
你在这儿干嘛?
What are you doing here?
- 我... 我不得不走来  - 什么?
- I... I had to walk.  - What?
他... 他说
He... he said everything
我们自以为知道的一切都是错的
that we thought we knew was wrong.
谁? 谁说的?
Who? Who did?
扫罗
Saul.
他已经成了耶稣的信徒了
He's become a follower of Jesus.
这主意很糟
This is a very bad idea.
告诉他
Tell him.
扫罗 你不能在犹太会堂
Saul, you can't preach the word of Jesus
传耶稣的道
inside the synagogue.
我们恰恰必须这样做
That is exactly what we have to do.
我明白你已经习惯
I understand that you're used to
仰仗权威的力量
having the weight of the authorities behind you.
如果他拣选我来宣扬他的名
If I have been chosen to proclaim his name,
那最好是今日而非明日
better I do it today than tomorrow,
最好是此时而非彼刻
better this hour than the next.
最好是此刻
Better this moment.
聚一下! 听我说!
Gather 'round! Listen to me!
我带来了消息!
I bring news!
我认为 只需要小小改变
I think, with a few changes
和一些想象力...
and a little imagination...
别操之过急了
Don't get ahead of yourselves.
提庇留还没做决定呢
Tiberius hasn't made his decision yet.
作为我的继任者 我为你做出了一个好榜样
I made a good case for you as my successor.
你永远不知道会发生什么
You never know what could happen.
好了
Enough of this.
我们得到了想要的
We have what we wanted.
知足就好
Let's just be grateful.
我... 以为你随着大帝离开了
I... thought you left with the emperor.
这多好啊?
Isn't that sweet?
一对毒蛇刚要离开
As one pair of vipers prepare to leave,
另一对就打算搬进来了
another plans to move in.
我的朋友! 我就知道他们不能把我们分开
My friend! I knew they couldn't keep us apart.
我带来了消息...
I bring news...
非常不好的消息
very grave news.
提庇留大帝...
Emperor Tiberius...
驾崩了
is dead.
出人意料
It's shocking news.
我真是...
I was...
非常震惊
shocked.
但我们应该感恩
We must be thankful.
我听说他睡在床上... 走得很安详
I'm told he died peacefully... in his bed.
你在期待罗马的新职位吗?
Were you looking forward to your new position in Rome?
多可惜啊
Such a shame.
你的丈夫在这个宫殿里
Your husband, in this palace,
用刀抵着我的喉咙
held a blade against my throat.
他真的很想我死
He really wanted me dead.
过去的就过去吧?
Can't that be left in the past?
没错
Yes.
你说得对
You're right.
让我们关注当下
Let's stay with the present.
那么...
So...
你的尊重在哪?
Where is your respect?
跪下!!
Kneel!!
跪拜你的新大帝!
In the presence of your new emperor!!
提庇留大帝...
Emperor Tiberius...
驾崩了
is dead.
新的威胁迫使不共戴天的仇敌结盟
With a new threat force two sworn enemies to become allies.
你能原谅我吗?
Can you forgive me?